你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院内核模块的第二个视频
welcome to the second video in the kernel module of pwn college
我们将讨论环境搭建
we're gonna be talking about environmental setup
为什么我们要谈这个
why are we gonna be talking about this
因为内核环境更复杂
well that's because it's more complicated for the kernel
相较于我们以前攻击的程序
than you are used to for the binaries we've been attacking so far
程序相对简单
binaries are relatively simple
他们就是ELF文件
they're an elf
他们有segment
they have you know segments
加载它们
you load them
就好了，简单
boom nice and simple
我们要深入研究的是更复杂的
what we're about to dive into is more complex
我们正在深入研究的是一个完整的环境
we're diving into an entire environment
一个运行着内核的完整系统
an entire system that running with a kernel
里面有用户空间程序
with user space binaries
有命令解释器
with command interpreters
有很多疯狂的东西
with quite a lot of you know crazy stuff inside them
我们要利用它
we're gonna be exploiting that
那么如何搭建这个环境呢
so how do we set up this environment
当然，你可以用你的电脑
well of course you could use your workstation
你说，我的电脑上就运行着内核
you say okay my workstation is running a kernel
没问题
no problem
我只要写一个内核模块
i'll just write a kernel module
载入它，黑掉它
load it hack it
但你可能会搞砸
but you likely mess up
要么你写的内核模块有bug
you either have a bug in your kernel module
要么利用程序中有bug
you have a bug in your exploit
你会把东西搞崩
you will crash stuff
当你在内核中把东西搞崩时
and when you crash them inside the kernel
正如我在之前的视频中所说的
as i talked about in the previous video
你在冒很大的风险
you're playing in high stakes
你在0环
you're in ring 0
这就不是一个段错误，就没事的了
it's not just a seg fault and go on with your day
你的整个电脑都会崩溃
your entire computer can crash
我第一次在课堂上教内核
my first time i taught the kernel in class
由于过度的信心，我用了自己的电脑
i used due to an overabundance of confidence my own workstation
我自己的笔记本电脑做演示
my own laptop for demos
不得不重启好几次
and had to reboot several times
所以，使用模拟环境要容易得多
so it's much easier to use an emulated environment
你可以用它来调试等等
with which you can play around debug and so on
为此，你需要一个编译器来编译环境
for this you'll need a compiler to compile the environment
编译将在环境中编写的程序
to compile programs that you'll write inside the environment
你利用漏洞进内核时
when you are launching exploits into the kernel
通常情况下，你是在用户空间启动的
typically you're doing that from user space binaries
所以你需要
so you need to
你的内核漏洞利用程序是一个用户空间的c程序
your exploits for the kernel will be user space c programs
它们以特定的方式与内核交互
that interact with the kernel in specific ways
当你
when you are
你在模拟系统中时
you will live inside inside your emulated system
会有一个用户空间
there will be a user space
一个小小的命令解释器等等
a tiny command interpreter and so on
要构建这个环境
you need to build that
你需要有这个
you need to have that
你还需要一个模拟器来运行所有这些
and you need to have an emulator to run all of this
我们在PWN学院代码仓库中，提供了一个方便的工具
we created a nice convenient setup for you under the pwn college repository
在GitHub的pwncollege组织下
under the pwn college organization at GitHub
叫pwnkernel
called pwnkernel
我们来看看
so let's take a look
这里，我已经用git下载了pwnkernel
here i have already checked out the pwn kernel repository
你可以看到这是readme
you can see this is the readme
readme很简单
and the readme is very simple
要搭建我的模拟环境
to build my emulator environment
只需执行build.sh
i just do build.sh
在录制这个视频之前，我已经构建过了
this i've already actually built it before recording this video
所以这里它只会做些检查
so this will just do a couple of checks
构建一些每次重建都要构建的东西
build some stuff that rebuilts every time
然后就好了
and then we're good to go
这里，你可以看到
you can see here
它创造了
it is creating
基本上是设置一个busybox用户空间
basically setting up a busybox user space
非常类似
very similar to the type of user space
许多路由器自带的，和嵌入式设备带的用户空间
that is shipped with a lot of routers and other embedded devices
非常小
very small
一个程序提供了
one single program that provides
你每天都会用到的很多工具的功能
the functionality of basically a lot of the normal tools you interact with on a daily basis
ls cp之类的
ls cp these sort of things
然后我们执行launch.sh
and then we do launch
launch.sh会把用户空间捆绑到一个文件系统中
launch will bundle up that user space into a file system
然后启动模拟器
and start the emulator
我们使用的模拟器是Q-emu
the emulator we're using is qemu
它把我们带入一个具有用户空间的模拟Linux系统
it drops us into an emulated Linux system with a user space
为了方便
for your convenience
我们给你提供了flag来玩
we even have a flag for you to play around with
有一些内核模块
there are kernel modules
一些预编译的内核模块样例
that are pre compiled example kernel module
我们将在下个视频中讨论它们
we'll talk about that in the next video
我现在不会讲到这个
i won't actually touch on that right now
基本上有你在Linux中所需要的一切
and basically there's everything you need to survive in Linux
这些都是链接到busybox的符号链接
i mentioned all of these are symbolic links to the busybox binary
然后busybox会根据你调用的方式
then busybox depending on how you invoked
看argv0是多少
what argv 0 is
扮演这些工具
will act like these different utilities
这是Linux中一个非常酷的系统
this is a very cool sort of system in linux
我们在这个内核中
so we are inside this kernel
我们可以做到
we can do
我们在一个模拟系统中
we are inside an emulated system
里面有一个模拟器
there's an emulator inside that
有一个内核在它认为是0环的地方运行
there's a kernel running in what it thinks is ring 0
在模拟器中的3环中
and then inside that or also inside emulator in ring 3
有一个正在运行的用户空间
there's a user space that's running
我还要提一件事
one extra thing i'll mention
对于小型漏洞利用环境非常有用
super super useful for these little exploitation environments
我们把你主机的~目录挂载到/home/ctf下
we mount your home directory from your host system in /home/ctf
所以当我进入/home/ctf/pwn/kernel
so i go /home/ctf/pwn/kernel
它是一样的
this is the same environment
和宿主机~/pwn/kernel/目录是一样的
the same files as in pwn/kernel in my normal machine
这意味着
that means
我可以在宿主机开发漏洞利用程序
i can do my exploit development on the normal machine
然后把这些漏洞利用程序编译出来
and then i take those exploits i compile them
然后执行它们
and i execute them
我在普通机器（宿主机）上编译
i compile them on my normal machine
因为模拟的机器中没有编译器
because there is no compiler inside the box
模拟的内核环境机器
the kernel box
然后我执行它们
and then i execute them
或者我可以写脚本
or for example i can write scripts
如果我输入/bin/sh
if i do /bin/sh
容器里没有bash
there's no bash inside the container
抱歉，模拟机器里没有bash
inside the the sorry inside the emulated machine
我可以执行echo hello
i can do echo hello
给它可执行权限
and i make that executable
好了，就这个hi.sh
and there it is hi.sh
这就很简单了
so this makes it very easy
启动一个screen会话
you launch a screen session you have
你在模拟系统中
you're inside the emulated system
你的实验环境
your experimental
或者做这个模块习题时的环境
or your challenge machine when you for the practice problems of this module
你将在我们设备上的模拟系统中，解决习题
you will be running those practice problems inside these emulated systems on our infrastructure
然后你可以在内部与它交互
and then you just interact with it from the inside
同时在外面正常开发
while being able to do your normal development from the outside
非常有用
super super useful okay
我们看看能用它做什么
let's take a look at what you can do with this
我们已经讲过了，有一个模拟器
so we've covered okay there is such a thing as emulation
你看到了我在模拟器里到处乱逛
you saw me inside that emulator wandering around
我们来谈谈调试
let's talk about debugging
很明显，当你启动
obviously when you launch
并开始在这个虚拟机中进行漏洞利用时
and start doing exploitation inside this virtual machine
你将需要进行调试
you will need to debug
幸运的是
luckily
我们为你提供了一个足够新的GDB
we have a new enough version of gdb for you
我们编译内核的时候开了调试选项
and we compile the kernel with debug symbols
在这个模块中，我们关闭了内核的地址空间随机化
and we have turned off address space randomization in the kernel for this module
至少在前几题中关了
or at least for the first couple of challenges that you will be interacting with for now
这些为真的前提下
with all of this true
你就可以合理地调试
you can debug reasonably
这意味着GDB会告诉你一些函数名，等等
that means that there are function names that gdb will tell you and so forth
我马上演示一下如何调试内核
so i'm going to jump into  and show you how to debug interactions with kernel
在我开始之前
before i go into this
回忆一下，执行syscall时
recall that when you do a syscall
如同上个视频中讲的
as i talked about in the previous module
会做几件事
you will do several things
将特权级别更改为ring 0
change your privilege level to ring 0
进入内核
you will jump into the kernel
跳转到，启动时将LSTAR指向的，syscall处理程序
into the syscall handler instruction that the kernel earlier set into the LSTAR register
还有将返回地址放在RCX中
and you will put the return address in rcx
我将向你们展示这一过程
i'm going to show you that happening
这三个步骤
all three of those effects
或至少两个
or at least two of them
第三个步骤不太好看出来
the third one is kind of hard to look at
现在我在宿主机上
here i am on my host machine
我要创建
i'm going to create
我会用一个普通的exit shellcode
i'm going to actually use some normal exit shellcode from my exit
就是shellcode模块的一个示例
just an example shellcode from the shellcode module
它就调用一个exit系统调用
all this does will call the exit syscall
在这儿
right here
我要编译它
and i'm going to compile this
很重要的一点是，要静态编译它
it's very important for these purposes to compile it statically
因为模拟环境中的用户空间中
because the user space inside the simulated kernel
如果我们看一下/lib
if we do find /lib
里面没有库
there are no libraries
甚至没有/lib这个目录
there isn't even /lib
没有ldd
there is no ldd
因为这里没有动态链接的程序
because there are no dynamicly linked binaries in here
没有文件
there's no file
但是如果我
but if i
进入
go into
这是打包前的文件系统
this is the unpacked file system before we
我们启动模拟器时
when we actually run the emulation
我们把build.sh放到一起的文件系统
we pack this this file system that build.sh puts together
打包成一个文档
into an archive
然后传给内核
that then gets passed into the kernel
模拟器启动时传给模拟器
into the emulator when the emulator runs
你不用担心这些
you don't have to worry about all this
这是未打包的版本
this is the unpacked version
如果你看一下busybox
if you look at busybox
它是一个静态链接的二进制文件
it is a statically linked binary
这里没有库
there are no libraries inside here
所以其他的东西也必须是静态连接的
so everything else has to be statically linked as well
因此，我们创建了一个静态链接库
so we create a statically linked library
默认情况下，这意味着它不是位置无关的
by default this means it won't be position independent
这很好
which is good
因为这样调试起来更容易
because it'll be easier for us to debug
我们开始吧
and here we go
然后-nosdlib
and then -nostdlib
好的，当然
okay of course
想用的话，这里也有assemble汇编工具
there's also the assemble command if you use shell tools
但
but that's
这个效果就很好
this works great
现在我们有了静态链接的exit程序
so now we have our exit executable statically linked
如果我们在模拟器外运行它
that if we just run it outside of the emulator
它就是调用exit，参数为0
it just calls exit zero
我们objdump它
so actually let's objdump it
这样就知道断点设置在哪里
so we know where to break
请原谅，这糟糕的AT&T语法
excuse the horrible AT&T syntax
我们断在这里，程序入口0x401000处
okay we're gonna break here the entry point 401000
看看会发生什么
see what happens
那么我们怎么做呢
so how can we do this
首先这里没有GDB
one there's no gdb in here
就算有，也帮不了我们
and it wouldn't help us if there was
因为我们想调试内核
because we want to debug the kernel
这里要讲的是调试内核
this is going to be all about debugging the kernel
不是用户空间
not the user space
所以我们启动它的方式，很酷
so the way that we launch this is actually super cool
如果我们
if we
对不起
sorry
launch.sh
我们用qemu作为我们的模拟器
we use qemu as our emulator
我们把-s参数传给qemu
and we pass the -s argument to qemu
这意味着在1234端口开启一个GDB服务
this means open up a gdb server port on port 1234
如果用GDB连接到该端口
and if you connect to that port from gdb
你就可以调试内核
you can debug the kernel
太酷了
that is going to be so cool
我们运行GDB
we run gdb
要给gdb什么文件，方便gdb读取有哪些函数之类的
and what file do we give to gdb for to read functions and stuff from
我们给它编译过的Linux内核
we will give it the Linux kernel that was compiled
它叫做vmlinux
it's called vmlinux
这也是一个ELF文件
this is also an ELF file
非常简单
very simple
非常标准
very standard actually
我的意思，这个简单是相对的
i mean simple is a relative term
如果我们反汇编它
so if we disassemble this
这是Linux内核
this is the Linux kernel
这是它的位置
this is where it's going to be at
这全是Linux内核
and then this is all of the Linux kernel
这太疯狂了
it's insane all right
这会很大
this is gonna be very large
看看反汇编结果有多少行
let's see how many lines of disassembly
这可能需要几分钟
this might take minutes
所以我可能一会就关了它
so i might kill it soonish
不用了
nope
Linux内核有
the Linux kernel has
6,682,034 行
six million, six hundred and eighty two thousand, and thirty four
反汇编结果，和objdump输出的空行之类的
lines of disassembly and white space and stuff from objdump
这太疯狂了
that's insane all right
我们可以用GDB加载它
so using gdb we can load it
这载入了Linux内核
so this loads the Linux kernel
现在我们要连接到1234端口
now we are going to attach to the port
这个模拟系统开的端口
that this running system has opened
qemu为我们打开的
that qemu has opened for us
我们执行remote
so we do remote
这只是一个网络端口
and this just a network port
TCP端口1234
TCP port 1234
好的，连上了
boom and we've attached
我们是
and we are
能看到，一切正常
so you can see everything is working
能正常显示函数名
because we have function names
我们在default_idle函数
we are at the default idle function
这意味着什么也没发生
that means nothing is happening
内核是空闲的
the kernel is idle
当然我们可以执行常规的命令
we can of course do the standard stuff
看看rip，等等
look at the instruction pointer etc etc
这就是内核空间
so this is kernel space
看看这个疯狂的地址
look at this crazy address
我们现在在内核地址空间
we're in kernel space now
我们已经不在用户空间了
we are not in user space anymore
当然
now of course
我们
we are
GDB暂停了系统
gdb has paused execution
我们查看一下
we are looking around
可以看到，如果我在这里输入
and as you can see if i start typing here
没反应
nothing's happening
continue后
if you continue execution boom
突然有反应了
something has happened all of a sudden
系统运行起来了
we're running again
我可以在这里按Ctrl c，再次中断执行
i can hit Ctrl c here to interrupt execution again
continue等等
continue and so forth
我们去到/home/ctf/pwn
let's go to /home/ctf/pwn
我们的exit在这里
and here's our exit right
不幸的是，我们这里没有strace
we don't have strace in here unfortunately
但如果你编译一个静态链接版本的strace
but if you compile strace statically linked
我们就可以在这里运行strace
we could run strace in here
但我们得相信exit调用了exit系统调用
but we'll have to trust that exit is calling the exit syscall
当然，是这样的
of course it is
可以看到返回值0
you can see the return value is 0
一切似乎都很好
all seems to be good
我们该如何调试它
now how do we debug this
我们如何调试内核
how do we debug the kernel
这个视频中，我想向你们展示
i want to show you for the purpose of this video
调用系统调用时，从用户空间到内核空间的过程
the transition from user space into kernel space when syscall is called
我们来看看
so let's take a look
提醒一下
just to remind ourselves
入口地址是401000
the entry point is 401000
停在这里
pause execution here
就像往常一样
and just like normal
在401000处创建一个断点
create a break point at 401000
这个不是内核地址
that's not a kernel address
不过没关系
but that's okay
我们能管理整个系统
we're in charge of the whole system
我们正在调试电脑
we're debugging the computer
qemu提供给我们的模拟电脑
the emulated computer that qemu is providing to us
这太不可思议了
this is incredible
哦，我不小心
oops i accidentally
创建了第二个断点，但是
it made a second breakpoint but
如果我执行info break
so if i do info break
这个是我们在入口地址处的断点
here's my break point at the entry point
我继续
i continue
然后我运行exit
and i run exit
它停住了
and it hangs
为什么会停
why does it hang
因为它触发了断点
because it dropped into my break point
这太酷了
how cool is that
我连入到
i am inside connected to
我在GDB中
i am in gdb
连入到正在模拟Linux系统的qemu
connected to qemu that is emulating a Linux system
我的exit程序在模拟系统里面运行
inside which my exit program is running
我在断点处打断了它
and i have interrupted it in a break point
所以我可以执行一个disp命令
so i can add a display
这是接下来要执行的指令
here's what's going to happen
它会xor eax,eax
it's going to xor eax
它会载入exit系统调用
it's going to load the exit call
然后它会
then it'll do
哦，exit系统调用码
oh the exit syscall number
然后它会运行syscall
and then it'll run syscall
当然，在上个视频中
of course in the last video
你还记得syscall的实质吧
you remember what the fact syscall has
我们马上看一下
we're going to observe them
我们si、si
so let's step step
这很可能是你以前从未见过的
this is something that you will never have seen before most likely
除非你以前见过
unless you've seen it before
通常如果你在这里si
normally if you do step instruction here
会直接执行完syscall
you'll just step past the syscall
现在系统调用将不再执行
the syscall will be executed no longer
我正在掀开面纱
i am peeling back the curtain
现在你能看到被调用的syscall
and you can see the syscall being called
这太酷了
this is super cool
我们在内核里面
we're inside the kernel
我们在内核里
并且我们在这个entry_SYSCALL_64里
and we're inside this entry syscall 64
64代表64位系统调用
64 for of course 64 bits entry syscall
我们在做各种各样不认识的疯狂的事情
we are doing all sorts of crazy stuff that we don't recognize
这些指令有一半很奇怪
half of these instructions are weird
这里有一些奇怪的段偏移
there's some some weird segment offset here
这基本上是内存中的一个指针
this is basically a pointer somewhere in memory essentially
这是从它开始的偏移量
and this is an offset off of it
有一个
there is a you know
这很复杂
it's complicated
我们刚刚进入了syscall指令内部
we've just walked into a syscall instruction
这太棒了
this is awesome
如果你还记得的话
if you recall
syscall不只是控制流的跳转
syscall not only transfer control flow here
它还会把返回地址放到rcx中
but it puts the return address into rcx
我们可以看到，RCX是41006
and as we can see rcx here is 41006
在这里
that is here
当然exit系统调用不会返回
of course the exit syscall doesn't return
进程终止了
the process is terminated
但我们就在这里
but there we are
有几件事
a couple of things
你可能习惯了用ni跳过call
you're probably used to doing next instruction to step over calls
这样你就不会陷得很深
so you don't go deep deep deep
这里ni似乎不好使
that seems to be broken
要么是ubuntu2004中我这个版本的gdb的问题
either in my version of gdb on 2004
要么是qemu中gdb的问题
or in some interactively gdb in Qemu
但能用的是
what does work
你可以用si
is you can do step instruction
我们这里要si多次
and we're gonna step instruction for a while here
最终
and eventually
我们会看到它保存了很多状态
we'll see it saving off a whole bunch of state
然后初始化一堆东西
and then initializing a bunch of stuff
保存了一堆东西
so saving a bunch of things
清零了一堆东西
and zeroing stuff out
它在执行这个push
and it's doing this push right
你可能会说
you might say oh you know
它把东西压入了栈
it's pushing stuff onto our stack
而我们在用户空间的栈似乎不太安全
and our stacks in userspace that doesn't seem very safe
一些内核秘密可能被泄露
some kernel secrets could be leaked
事实并非如此
that's not the case
如果我们向上看
it if we scroll up
会看到它将栈切换到了内核栈
we'll see it actually changing the stack to be our kernel stack
总之
anyways
我们进入
let's walk in
这个do_syscall函数
this is the do syscall function
它会找出要执行哪个系统调用
which will actually figure out which syscall to do
然后执行
and then do it
这个入口点保存了所有的状态
this entry point just saves all the state
执行系统调用
does the syscall
然后当系统调用返回时
and then when the syscall returns
它会恢复状态
it'll restore the state
然后返回，一会儿会si到
and return will step through that in a sec
我不能ni
i can't do ni
它会崩溃
it's gonna break
所以我执行si
so i'm gonna do si
我现在在do_syscall
i'm now inside do syscall
在这里，我执行finish
and in here i just do finish
它会一直运行到该syscall退出
and it'll run until exit from that syscall
当然
and of course
我猜那个syscall一直不会退出
i'm guessing that that syscall never returns
因为它是exit
because it's exit
我换个syscall试一下
let me do a different syscall real quick
试一下read
let's just do read
还是试一下sendfile
let's do sendfile
Sendfile是40
sendfile is 40
所以我们改成40
so we do 40
我们mov rax, 1 抱歉，不是rax
we'll mov rax 1 sorry not rax
mov rdi 1
所以我们的第一个参数out是标准输出
so our first argument the out is our standard out
in是标准输入
the in is our standard in
我们mov RDX 0
we will move rdx 0
第三个参数是偏移量
the third argument is the offset
然后是r10
and then r10
是r10还是r8
is that r10 or 8
我懵了
i just went blank
我需要更多的睡眠
i need more sleep
是r10
it is r10
我刚查了一下
i just looked it up
真不敢相信我脑子一片空白
i can't believe i went blank
好的，然后r10赋值为128
okay and then 128
这会执行一次sendfile
so this will just do a sendfile once
我们重新
let's do the same
不对，错了
nope wrong one
用assemble汇编sendfile.s
just assemble using this sendfile.s
好的sendfile
okay sendfile
为什么段错误
why segfault
我搞砸了什么
what am i screwing up
哦
oh
sendfile可能不能
sendfile probably can't
不管它是什么
it doesn't matter what it is
执行一个系统调用就行
it'll just do a system call
我们看一下它调用系统调用
and we're going to watch it doing a system call
入口点的偏移量保持不变
the offset of the entry point remains the same
所以断点仍然有效
so our break point is still valid
我们运行sendfile
so let's run sendfile
好了，我们在断点了
okay here we're at the break point
设置调用条件中
set up everything
执行syscall
syscall
我们到内核了
boom we're in the kernel
步过这些初始化
step step step step through all of this initialization
好了，进入到do_syscall_64
okay step into the call
finish好了
finish okay
函数返回了
that one returned
接着步过
now you can step step step
我想展示一下回到用户空间的sysret指令
and i want to show you the sysret instruction where we go back into user space
现在我们开始恢复保存的状态
here we go we're restoring the saved states
开头使用了一堆push保存状态
use all those push in the beginning that saves the state
现在我们恢复这些状态
and now we're restoring it
这里甚至还恢复了用户空间栈指针
and here is even restoring the user space stack pointer
之前是内核栈
before it's our stack pointer is in the kernel
现在的栈指针rsp
now our stack pointer
仍然在内核中
it is still in the kernel
还没有恢复
hasn't restored yet
哦
ooh
这里在动CR3寄存器
the cr3 register we're messing around with it
好的，pop RSP
here we go pop rsp
之后我们用sysret返回用户空间
and then we'll do a sysret to go back to user space
这里跟我们的内核栈说再见了
so here is say goodbye to our kernel stack
回到用户空间栈
back to user space stack
执行sysret
and sysret
我们回到了用户空间
and we're back in user space of course
这些是syscall返回后，的垃圾数据
and the garbage that is after our syscall
这太酷了
how cool is that
当然，syscall返回到了rcx
and of course that returned back to rcx
这就是调试一个运行中内核的过程
that was us debugging a running kernel
非常令人兴奋的东西
very exciting stuff
我们也可以设置一个断点
we can also put a break point actually
我们禁用第一个断点
let's disable the first break point
可以在entry_syscall或do_syscall函数本身上设置断点
you can put a break point on the entry_syscall or the do_syscall function itself
我们怎么才能找到它
how do we find where that is
有两种方法
there are two ways
一是,如果我们有内核镜像
one if we have the kernel image
我们就可以用objdump
we can use objdump of course
所以我们可以执行objdump -d Linux vmlinux
so we can do objdump -d Linux vmlinux
实际上最好使用nm -a Linux vmlinux
actually better use nm -a Linux vmlinux
grep查找do_sycall
and grep for do_syscall
就是这个
here it is
太好了
that's great
现在我们知道该断在哪里了
so now we know where to break
内核本身也提供了一个很棒的功能
there's also an awesome functionality provided by the kernel itself
我快速过一遍
actually let me go real quick over
看幻灯片
to the slides
内核本身在/proc/kallsyms中提供了
functionality provided by the kernel itself in /proc/k all syms
它会打印出一个符号列表
which will print out basically a list of symbols
如果我们回到这里
so if we go back to the to here
/proc/kallsyms
哦，该死，我关了我的系统
oh shit i killed my system
要非常小心
be very careful
如果你按了ctrl c
if you do control
我们这里启动Qemu的方式
the way that we launch Qemu here
qemu不拦截特殊键
so that it's not trivially escapable through special key presses that Qemu interprets
它不会拦截ctrl c
it won't catch control c
如果你ctrl c
if you control c
整个模拟器都关了
that whole emulator is dead
幸运的是，/home/ctf下的文件是持久的（挂载的~）
luckily again files and home ctf are persistent
这些是内核所有符号的地址
these are all of the symbol addresses of the kernel
搞砸了，这要很长时间
i screwed up because this is gonna take forever
我们可以grep do_sycall
okay and we can grep do_syscall
显然有很多处理函数
obviously there are many handlers
这里和这里的地址是一样的
and here this is the same address as this
有个叫内核地址空间随机化的东西
now there is such a thing as kernel address space randomization
现在是禁用的
for now is disabled
我们以后再谈
we'll talk about it later
所以现在这些都是可以预测的
so for now these are always predictable
该方法只适用于拥有root权限的情况
this only works if you have root access inside your machine
如果你没有root权限
if you don't have root access
也没有这些地址的信息源
and you don't have a source of those addresses
比如内核映像
such as the kernel image
你就有麻烦了
you're in trouble
你必须要像绕过aslr一样，泄露地址
you have to have a leak similar to ASLR
但有了root权限
but with root access
你可以直接查找
you can look all this up
现在我们有了这个地址
so now we have this address
我们当然可以在这里设一个断点
we can of course put a break point here
哦
oops
我们需要重新连接
we need to reconnect
因为我不小心关了内核
because i killed the kernel accidently okay
我们附加上了
so we we've attached
我们可以在do_sycall设置一个断点
we can put a break point at do_syscall
我们继续
we continue
现在不管我们要干什么
and then now anything we run
就算只是在shell中打字
including just typing into my shell
都会触发这个断点
will trigger this break point
很酷吧
very cool huh
当然我们可以
and we can of course
看看会发生什么
see what's going to happen
继续
continue and of course
有大量，不同的系统调用号
there are tons and tons of syscalls of different numbers
read系统调用
read syscall
任何系统调用
whatever syscall
7是
seven is
我们看看syscall 7是什么
let's see what syscall seven is
是poll
poll
等等
and so forth yeah
shell的一个普通操作涉及了许多系统调用
a lot of syscalls going on in the normal operation of my shell
如果你像这样调试
so if you do your debugging like this
你可能需要更具体的断点
you might want to be a little more specific about where you break
一个好方法就是像我之前那样
but a good way to debug is actually like i did
断在一个你知道的用户空间地址
you break at inside a userspace binary an address you know
然后从那里开始
and then you follow from there
另外
alternatively
如果你正在调试内核模块
if you're debugging kernel module
那就在正在调试的内核模块内部进行中断
then break specifically inside the kernel module you're debugging
我们下个视频再讲内核模块
we'll talk about that next video
如果你真的对这些感兴趣的话
if you're really interested in all of this
这有些阅读材料
some further reading
这里描述了如何搭建内核漏洞利用环境
here's a description of how we set up a kernel exploit environment
当然，你也可以阅读pwnkernel的源代码
or you can of course read the source code of pwn kernel
有一个关于内核调试的完整文档
there's an entire document on kernel debugging
从在qemu中运行内核
from running the kernel in qemu
到在GDB进行调试
and debugging from gdb
就是我刚刚快速展示的
what i just showed off real quick
还有一个功能更丰富
and a much more feature-rich
类似于pwnkernel的环境配置
kind of analog to pwnkernel
在那里你可以探索
where you can explore
你可以尝试不同的架构
you can experiment with different architectures
arm上的Linux内核，等等
Linux kernel on arm etc etc
不同的内核版本
different kernel versions
功能更丰富
much more feature rich
下一个视频将讨论内核模块
next video talk about kernel modules